{"tossups": [{"question": "The city of Bagram was originally the capital of an ethnically Greek state that practiced this religion. Two statues of this religion's founder at Bamiyan (<b>pr. BAY-mee-yahn</b>) were destroyed by the Taliban. For 10 points, name this religion whose Vajryana (<b>pr. VAHJ-rye-AH-nuh</b>) form is practiced in Tibet by followers of the Dalai Lama.", "answer": "<b><u>Buddhism</u></b>", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "Near the end of his life, this man gave a speech identifying the \"three boxes\" as the source of rights. This man was nominated for Vice-President by the Equal Rights Party on the Victoria Woodhull ticket. This orator gave a speech asking \"what, to the slave, is the Fourth of July\" after founding <em>The North Star</em>. This author of <em>My Bondage and My Freedom</em> wrote about his escape from Mr. Covey in Maryland. For 10 points, name this former slave turned abolitionist.", "answer": "Frederick <b><u>Douglass</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Along with Henry David Thoreau, this thinker was cited as the chief Western influence on Gandhi. His pacifist tome <em>The Kingdom of God is Within You</em> made him the leader of dissenting Christians in early twentieth century Russia. For 10 points, name this man who viewed his theological work as more important than his novels, such as <em>Anna Karenina</em>", "answer": "Leo <b><u>Tolstoy</u></b> [Lev Nikolayevich <b><u>Tolstoy</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This event was set in motion when Abel Corbin introduced its two plotters to the President, and Daniel Butterfield agreed to pass along inside information. This 1869 event tainted the Grant administration and was an attempt by James Fisk and Jay Gould to \"corner\" the gold market. For 10 points, identify this day, which shares its name with a post-Thanksgiving shopping event.", "answer": "<b><u>Black Friday</u></b> (prompt on Friday)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This king ordered the destruction of all remaining Protestant churches in the Edict of Fontainebleau (<b>pr. FAHN-tohn-blow</b>). He was opposed at his accession by the Fronde movement, which was countered by his early advisor, Cardinal Mazarin. For 10 points, name this monarch who reigned for seventy-two years as the absolutist \"Sun King\" of France.", "answer": "<b><u>Louis XIV</u></b> [prompt on <b><u>Louis</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man headed the Firebird and GTO projects while he was chief engineer of Pontiac, prior to starting his own namesake company. In 1982, he was arrested for participating in a cocaine deal, which he was acquitted of at trial after arguing entrapment. For 10 points, identify this man whose car firm produced a gull-winged, unpainted steel car used in <em>Back to the Future</em>.", "answer": "John <b><u>DeLorean</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This party was victimized by the Zinoviev letter hoax, which purported to show Soviet control of its operations and brought down its first prime minister, Ramsay Macdonald. This party was first represented in Parliament by Scottish coal miner Keir Hardie. For 10 points, name this party, now the more left-wing of the two largest political parties in the United Kingdom.", "answer": "<b><u>Labour</u></b> Party", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Zacharias Janssen may have invented the first version of this device, which was first used in biology by Anton van Leeuwenhoek (<b>pr. LAY-ven-hoke</b>). In 1932, Ernst Ruska pioneered the \"electron\" type of this device, which was used to discover cells in cork by Robert Hooke. For 10 points, identify this device which lens-grinders created to peer at tiny objects.", "answer": "<b><u>microscope</u></b>", "metadata": "Science - Physics"}, {"question": "This man's prominent depiction on the cover of <em>When the Word Is Given</em> offended his superiors, as did his commentary that the John F. Kennedy assassination was \"a case of chickens coming home to roost.\" He was killed at the Audubon Ballroom, most likely by agents of Elijah Muhammad. For 10 points, name this chief spokesman for the Nation of Islam.", "answer": "<b><u>Malcolm X</u></b> [or Malcolm <b><u>Little</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In the autumn of 1649, this man led armies which sacked Drogheda (pr. <b>DRAH-huh-dah</b>), leading to his reputation as a cruel conqueror of Ireland. He was succeeded by his son Richard after his death. For 10 points, name this leader of the New Model Army who attained supreme power as \"Lord Protector of England\" after the Civil War.", "answer": "Oliver <b><u>Cromwell</u></b> <b>NHBB C 2014-2015 - Bowl Round 2 - Second Quarter </b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "The \"foundations\" of this field were described in a book by David Hilbert, and its \"hyperbolic\" form was pioneered by J\u00e1nos Bolyai (<b>pr. YAH-nowsh BOWL-yai</b>) and the Russian Nikolai Lobachevsky (<b>pr. LOH-buh-CHEFF-skee</b>). For 10 points, name this math field whose foundational text is the <em>Elements</em> by Euclid (<b>pr. YOOK-lid</b>), which discusses the parallel postulate and Pythagorean theorem.", "answer": "<b><u>geometry</u></b>", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Math"}, {}, {"question": "This artist depicted Nazi concentration camp victims in <em>The Charnel House</em>. In the late 1940s, this wealthy artist was the primary financial backer of the French Communist Party. An earlier political painting by him shows a lightbulb, a horse, and a screaming woman in memory of a Basque village bombed by the Nazis. For 10 points, name this creator of <em>Guernica</em>.", "answer": "Pablo <b><u>Picasso</u></b> [Pablo Ruiz y <b><u>Picasso</u></b>]", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "This city\u2019s former troops revolted against it in the Mercenary War. As a result, this city's leader Hanno the Great was displaced by the rising Barcid dynasty, whose members included Hamilcar and Hasdrubal. This city lost the Battle of Zama to Scipio Africanus. For 10 points name this ancient North African city which was defeated by Rome in three Punic Wars.", "answer": "<b><u>Carthage</u></b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "In the 1950s, this team was led by quarterback Y.A. Tittle and the \"Million Dollar Backfield.\" This team's receiver Dwight Clark made \"The Catch\" in 1982, and in January 1995, with quarterback Steve Young, they became the first NFL team to win a fifth Super Bowl. For 10 points, name this team that won four titles under the leadership of Joe Montana.", "answer": "<b><u>San Francisco</u></b> 49ers [or <b><u>49ers</u></b>]", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {"question": "Soon after independence, this country fell under the domination of the \"hairy feet\" secret police of Jos\u00e9 de Francia. This country was ruled by the eccentric Francisco Solano Lopez when it lost the majority of its male population to the War of the Triple Alliance. For 10 points, identify this country which has developed oddly due to its landlocked position in South America.", "answer": "<b><u>Paraguay</u></b> [Republic of <b><u>Paraguay</u></b>] [or Republica del <b><u>Paraguay</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "A powerful official in this government was the \"censor,\" who determined eligibility for the Senate. Politicians under this government followed the \"cursus honorum\" to move through the ranks of aedile (<b>pr. EY-dial</b>), quaestor (<b>pr. KWAI-stor</b>), praetor (<b>pr. PRAI-tor</b>), and finally become one of two consuls. For 10 points, name this governmental system which was replaced by the Empire.", "answer": "Roman <b><u>Republic</u></b> (do not accept Senate)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "A bronze age museum is maintained at a \"crannog\" in County Clare on this island. This island regained its independence from Viking kingdoms at the 1014 Battle of Clontarf, re-establishing the High King's seat at the hill of Tara. The Book of Kells can be seen at Trinity College Library on this island. For 10 points, name this island, also home to the James Joyce Museum in Dublin.", "answer": "<b><u>Ireland</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "A desire to control this site sparked a brief 1860s war between France and Siam. This complex was built by Suryavarman II (<b>pr. SIR-yuh-VAHR-munthe second</b>) in the early twelfth century and dedicated to Vishnu, though it was later used for Buddhist worship. For 10 points, identify this Khmer (<b>pr. kuh-MARE</b>) Kingdom temple complex, or \"wat,\" in what is now Cambodia.", "answer": "<b><u>Angkor</u></b> Wat", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>Buffalo Springfield insisted that the song \"For What It's Worth\" was about the Sunset</u></b> <b><u>Strip curfew riots and not this event. This event was the subject of Country Joe and the</u></b> <b><u>Fish's biggest hit. A veteran of this conflict is the subject of (+)</u> Bruce Springsteen's \"Born in the USA,\" and a (*)</b> protest against this conflict inspired Neil Young to write \"Ohio\" about the Kent State shootings. For 10 points, name this war which inspired copious protest music in the late 1960s.", "answer": "<b><u>Vietnam</u></b> War", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>In 1844, the U.S. dispatched missionary Peter Parker and attorney Caleb Cushing to this</u></b> <b><u>country to negotiate a trade pact. This country signed the 1868 Burlingame Treaty with the</u></b> <b><u>United States. This country's natives were the subject of the (+)</u> Geary Act, and were prohibited from entering the U.S. between 1882 and 1943 under a namesake (*)</b> \"Exclusion Act.\" For 10 points, name this country which is now, after Canada, the second-largest trade partner of the U.S.", "answer": "<b><u>China</u></b> [or People's Republic of <b><u>China</u></b>, etc.; no one formal name applies to all periods referenced in the question]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>An important 1878 piece for this instrument was composed for the virtuoso Joseph</u></b> <b><u>Joachim (</u></b><u>pr. YO-zef YO-ah-keem</u><b><u>). This instrument was played by a composer of (+)</u></b> <b>twenty-four caprices who allegedly made a deal with the devil, Niccol\u00f2 (*) </b>Paganini. Many valuable examples of this instrument were created by the master craftsman Antonio Stradivari. For 10 points, name this string instrument which an orchestra's concertmaster plays.", "answer": "<b><u>violin</u></b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "<b><u>This organization was formed at the suggestion of Mary White Ovington following the</u></b> <b><u>Springfield riot of 1908, and it absorbed many veterans of the Niagara Movement. This</u></b> <b><u>organization awards the (+)</u> Spingarn Medals, and its first major effort was publishing</b><em><b> The </b><b>Crisis </b></em><b>under the editorship of (*)</b> W.E.B. DuBois (<b>pr. doo-BOYZ</b>). For 10 points, name this organization which led the anti-segregationist movement for much of the twentieth century.", "answer": "<b><u>NAACP</u></b> [<b><u>National Association for the Advancement of Colored People</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This man won a Nobel Prize in Literature for his</u> </b><em><b><u>History of the English-Speaking</u></b></em> <em><b><u>Peoples</u></b></em><b><u>. This man was First Lord of the Admiralty during the (+)</u> Gallipoli disaster, though his \"wilderness years\" eventually ended and allowed him to make the \"we shall (*)</b> fight them on the beaches\" speech. He was defeated in his first re-election bid by Clement Attlee. For 10 points, name this leader of the national unity government of the U.K. during World War II.", "answer": "Winston <b><u>Churchill</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Members of this organization were represented in the Reichstag by the Centre Party.</u></b> <b><u>This organization was targeted by Adalbert von Falk's May Laws, part of the (+)</u></b> <b>Kulturkampf (</b>pr. KOOL-tur-kompf<b>) against it launched by Otto von Bismarck. A leader of this organization who was accused of turning a blind eye to the Holocaust was (*)</b> Pius XII. For 10 points, name this organization which is the predominant Christian denomination in southern Germany.", "answer": "Roman <b><u>Catholic</u></b> Church", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>People who opposed this action wrote under the pen names Cato, Brutus, and the</u></b> <b><u>Federal Farmer, and were most likely George Clinton, Robert Yates, and Mercy Otis</u></b> <b><u>Warren. This action was supported in a series of (+)</u> letters to the </b><em><b>New York Packet </b></em><b>written by \"Publius,\" a collective pseudonym for James (*)</b> Madison, John Jay, and Alexander Hamilton. For 10 points, what was this action which was advocated in the Federalist Papers and created the present U.S. government?", "answer": "<b><u>ratifying</u></b> the U.S. <b><u>Constitution</u></b> [or equivalents]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>The first-ever U.S. Cabinet member to serve a prison sentence did so as a result of this</u></b> <b><u>scandal. This scandal's investigation by Thomas Walsh led to the Supreme Court case of</u></b> <em><b><u>McGrain v. Daugherty</u></b></em><b><u>, which held that Congress may require people to testify. It involved</u></b> <b><u>(+)</u> land in the Black Hills which Albert Fall, the Secretary of the Interior, leased to(*) </b>oil prospectors at cut rates. For 10 points, identify this defining scandal of the Warren Harding administration.", "answer": "<b><u>Teapot Dome</u></b>  <b>NHBB C 2014-2015 </b> <b>Bowl Round 2 </b> <b>Tiebreakers/extras \u2013 ONLY READ IF YOU NEED A BACKUP OR TIEBREAKER! </b> <b><u>This city was the site of a Church council held five years before the Council of Constance</u></b> <b><u>which elected Alexander V as Pope in an attempt to end the Western Schism. This city was</u></b> <b><u>the loser of the Battle of (+)</u> Meloria, and it was where a man allegedly dropped (*) </b>cannonballs out of a window in order to measure acceleration. For 10 points, name this home to a gravitational experiment by Galileo, who made use of an architectural blunder that created its \"leaning tower.\"  ANSWER: <b><u>Pisa</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}